there's a diet that's been proposed and for good
reason to completely eradicate heart disease
as in it's claimed that if you eat this diet
it eliminates heart disease even if you have
heart disease giving you 100% protection from any
cardiovascular event like a heart attack stroke or
anything related that idea has been popularized
by a physician and scientist Dr cowwell Eelstein
who has published several studies on the matter so
I'd like to open up some of these studies get to
the bottom of the topic and then introduce you to
some nuances that I think are often illcribed the
study that's most popular is this one and by the
title you can see why in this study researchers
including Dr aselstein who we'll hear from later
had 198 highly motivated people that started on an
extreme diet the diet was simply characterized as
a whole food plant-based and importantly oilfree
diet all oils are prohibited in addition to any
animal products as well as nuts avocados excess
salt caffeine kill me now and if you're wondering
what these people were allowed to eat whole grains
legumes lentils vegetables and fruits since these
participants were highly motivated considering
that they had coronary artery disease they were
on this diet for an average of 3.7 years and
then the researchers measured the plaque in the
arteries before and after the diet for some of the
participants as well as tracked if the disease
presented itself in all participants as in did
some experienced cardiovascular issues during
that time in fact the most impressive results
are shown here on the left is the left anterior
descending artery which is the artery of the heart
that's often called the widow maker because it's
so deadly if it's blocked you can see on the left
image the vessel is much thinner than in the post
image on the right side which shows a thickening
of the white space so that's called the lumen of
the artery that means that the body was able to
remove the plaque and reopen the artery which is
an incredible image i mean truly this is further
confirmed by this image the coloration there
indicates the amount of blood flow to the heart
specifically the myioardium a section of the heart
the top is before the diet and the bottom is after
the diet again a massive difference now I call
this the most impressive results and they are
but they are also disappointing in some key ways
well for one these are representative images but
as far as I could tell uh no averages so across
all the participants were reported in this study
this is important because someone could just show
images of an outlier a person who did better than
everyone else in this instance and bamboozle us
all i don't think that actually happened here
for reasons that we're about to get into but it's
still a weakness of the study a second weakness is
the fact that this wasn't a controlled study as
in there was no control group so to see if there
were results that might also be experienced in the
control group taking some power away from the idea
that this specific diet causes these benefits
practically this probably doesn't matter much
but scientifically it matters on the other hand
the researchers reported the number of people
who experienced actual cardiac events like heart
attacks and strokes and those results are also
remarkable and displayed here on the left are
the adherent participants so people who stuck to
this restrictive diet that we discussed earlier
and the right side is 21 individuals who were
banished from this land for rebelling against
the king or they were just people who didn't
stick to the diet as well as they should have just
couldn't resist having coffee i empathize we also
see outcomes which is the cardiovascular outcomes
like anga or chest pain due to likely a lack of
blood flow to the heart as we can see 105 of 177
individuals experienced improvements in symptoms
39 experienced actual reversal and 15 remain
stable leaving 18 individuals as getting worse now
at the beginning of this video we discussed 100%
protection from cardiovascular events so how could
people be getting worse if they were adhering
to this diet well I'll let Dr eslestein answer
that in our in our 2014 paper yeah yes there was
one patient who had uh gone on vacation to China
absolutely began eating off the economy he had a
tendency to have hypertension and of course all
the salt and he had a small cerebellar stroke
mhm he did not follow the program he is the
one in the com he was somehow made it into the
compliant group that not compliance going off on
the economy and so really therefore in that
group nobody had an event for close to four
years 177 patients so Dr rasselstein's point is
that one person was mischaracterized as compliant
or adherent when in reality they were not which
is why they experienced a stroke i assume that's
this one here and then several more participants
had cardiovascular issues due to according to
the researchers unrelated reasons for example
undergoing a heart surgery on the advice of
their physician so in the best case scenario the
diet did not result in any cardiovascular events
and the worstc case scenario 10% of people still
experienced an event related or unrelated the nice
thing about reporting the non-adherent individuals
is that they can make a comparison between the
diet and not following the diet it's not a true
control group but it offers a comparison in that
people who did not follow the diet so 62%
got worse and none got better that's a stark
difference compared to the people who are adherent
now there's a few things to say about this all
before that there are multiple studies using
varying diets to show arterial plaque reversal
so what I did was compile all these studies and
identify the trends across all these diets and
identify what are the likely greatest factors i
put them together into a guide that I wrote out
for the Physionic Insiders if you're interested
the link to join is in the description i promise
it's far less restrictive than the no oil diet
specifics that we're about to go over check it out
okay so depending on how we look at things this no
oil diet seems to significantly improve the odds
of not experienced cardiovascular issues i think
some of my hesitation related to this diet is
that the studies that have been done on it because
there's actually another one that's uh been done
like uh 12 years with a much smaller group but
showed similar amazing results both of them have
absolutely horrid study design i realize I'm going
to get some flak from the uh plant-based community
here but there's a lot to say here and I really
think that I'm being fair including my final point
that I'm going to make okay first as I alluded
none of these studies are controlled studies so
no randomization no researcher blinding no power
calculations no controls and so on second many of
these studies rely on categorical data and don't
report much on average data including standard
errors and the like we have to trust that the
researchers assessment of what is significant and
what is not significant while average data leaves
it up to the reader the analyzer third actually
let me uh turn to Dr carvalo's uh question
in his interview with Dr eelstein the video
uh to this walls will be linked underneath for
you too so that was one of the questions I had
and I've had people ask me that why hasn't there
been after all this time as as you said Dr orish
and your work has been around for 30 plus years
very interesting encouraging findings why hasn't
someone taken that and run a randomized trial just
with with your diet very low fat plant exclusive
or plant overwhelmingly plant and seen if it
reverses heart disease it's surprising to me that
that hasn't been done this is such a good question
because it's been something like 30 years of us
getting these uh methodologically weak studies
to indicate that this diet works especially
when we have many many studies that look at other
nutrition styles and their cardiovascular effects
including some in plaque reversal let's hear Dr
esleston's perspective on why a randomized control
trial has not been done well in a sense there's
never any any nutrition in medical school that is
worth that it's worth its weight i mean maybe in
your freshman or sophomore year you get a lecture
on cholesterol but not on the fact that it can
actually eliminate men the leading killer of women
and men in Western civilization now there are
other things that I've always resisted as a reason
why people haven't jumped on it they cardiology
never gets any training in nutrition even in their
cardiology years when we when we did it out of the
American college of cardiology we did that survey
and in the cardiologists themselves conceded they
get very little at it's ne negligible the amount
of nutrition training they get so when they when
they are never trained in the cure of the disease
or or for that matter they're never trained in
the causation of the disease then it's no great
surprise and also when you are doing not everybody
has uh sparks flying out of their eyes when they
are asked to spend a half an hour talking with
a patient day after day after day after day with
nutrition how to do it now there are some of
us who have that quirk about us that seem to
enjoy that now the other one I have avoided for
the longest time but I'm going to say it today
how much do you suppose you get paid for bypass
surgery how much do you suppose you get paid for
stances or for heaping drugs onto people compared
to talking to somebody about Brussels sprouts and
broccoli mhm i mean there's a huge financial uh
situation here that and almost every hospital
worth its salt the biggest bottom line figure on
their of that hospital comes from their treatment
of cardiovascular disease yeah yeah i'm sure
it's a factor um but yeah I would love to see
in addition to all the trials that people are
carrying out with Mediterranean diets and with
DASH diets it would be really interesting to see a
trial where these different dietary approaches are
compared side by side uh so we can have some more
conclusive answers um I don't see how you can ask
a patient to to eat one of those diets when it's
never been shown to arrest reverse disease i I
don't know how an IRB would ever close when they
when we've got data that shows it doesn't have
to happen okay there's a lot there i don't doubt
that financial interests are a motivating or in
this case a demotivating factor i also don't doubt
that a lack of education in the medical field on
nutrition is a player however that doesn't explain
why we have so many trials on so many other diets
doing exactly what we're asking of this diet
so scientists and clinicians are uneducated on
nutrition when it comes to an oilfree plant-based
nutrition but they suddenly spring into action if
it's a DASH diet or the Mediterranean diet and
so on that reasoning doesn't exactly square in
addition saying that it's unethical to put people
on these diets seems a little extreme to me
especially when we have better evidence more solid
evidence for the aforementioned reason indicating
that they're profound positive cardiovascular
impact finally allow me to mention that I realize
I'm being a bit harsh here there are multiple
reasons for that that I'm disappointed that
this kind of controlled study hasn't been done in
decades uh I'm also annoyed because the uh strong
rhetoric that gets enunciated yet the evidence
while impressive is if we're being unbiased very
weak methodologically speaking finally I actually
believe Dr eselstein's results and these studies
but they aren't being contextualized correctly
and I can't in good faith argue this no oil diet
is actually better without any true comparative
studies so the takeaway here is that there is some
extremely impressive but methodologically flawed
evidence that indicates a no oil plant-based diet
severely cuts down and possibly eliminates future
atherosclerosis related cardiovascular disease
risk in people with already known cardiovascular
disease actually Dr dr eelstein even argues that
olive oil causes heart disease which I cover in
this next video including randomized studies on
other diets that significantly improve
heart disease i'll see you over there